Guide to the Harold Smith Papers ALBA.099
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harold Smith Papers
1937-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Smith, Harold
ALBA.099
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Harold Smith served as a volunteer with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War. He was born in New York City on January 4, in either 1910 or 1912 (a later record differs, but a copy of his passport record lists him as aged 27 in 1937). He attended City College, joined the Communist Party in 1934, and worked as a trade-union organizer. He listed his occupation as "clerk" in 1937. He sailed to Europe in February 1937 and, after a stop-over in Paris, arrived in Spain in mid-March. Smith was wounded twice in combat. He recovered sufficiently to fight in the Ebro action around Villalba, and returned to the U.S. on the SS Ausonia in December 1938. After the war, Smith taught at the League for Seriously Disturbed Children. He died in 1970. The collection consists of twenty-four handwritten letters written in Spain. Most are from Smith to his girlfriend, identified only as "Jeanette." One is from Smith to his sister(?) Clara, and one from a friend and fellow volunteer, Harry "Jack" Boxer, to "Jeanette."
Historical/Biographical Note
Harold Smith served as a volunteer with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War. He was born in New York City on January 4, in either 1910 or 1912 (a later record differs, but a copy of his passport record lists him as aged 27 in 1937). He attended City College, joined the Communist Party in 1934, and worked as a trade-union organizer. He listed his occupation as "clerk" in 1937. He sailed to Europe in February 1937 and, after a stop-over in Paris, arrived in Spain in mid-March. His letters home reflect an eager interest in the political deveopment of his friends and fellow Branch members, and in his union. Smith was wounded twice in combat. After suffering an arm wound he spent time in the Hospital Militar-Moya in Barcelona, where one of his nurses was U.S. volunteer Toby Jensky. He recovered sufficiently to fight in the Ebro action around Villalba, and returned to the U.S. on the SS Ausonia in December 1938. After the war, Smith became a member of the Board of Governors of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) and taught for a while at the League for Seriously Disturbed Children. He died in 1970.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in one series: I. Correspondence, 1937-1938.
Files are arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronoloigcally, with several undated fragments at the end.
Related Archival Material
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Provenance
The Harold Smith Papers came to the Tamiment Library as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University, in 2001.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of twenty-four handwritten letters written in Spain. Most are from Smith to his girlfriend, identified only as "Jeanette." One is from Smith to his sister(?) Clara, and one from a friend and fellow volunteer, Harry "Jack" Boxer, to "Jeanette." Three items are undated fragments. Several of Harold Smith's original letters are accompanied by typed transcripts.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans -- United States -- Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain.; Smith, Harold; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Correspondence, 1937-1938
  Scope and Content Note
  The series consists mostly of letters sent by Harold Smith from Spain to a girlfriend, identified only as "Jeanette." Also included are one letter to his sister(?) Clara, one from a fellow volunteer, Harold "Jack" Boxer, ansd three undated fragments.
  - Boxer, Harry (Jack) to Jeanette, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Feb 27, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Mar 20, 22, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, May 16, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jun 11, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jun 25, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jul 22, 28, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Sep 1, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Nov 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Dec 13, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jan 9, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Mar 3, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Mar 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Smith, Harold to Clara, Apr 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jun 18, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jul 5, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Jul 22, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Aug 3, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Sep 5, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Oct 13, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Smith, Harold to Jeanette, Oct 14, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Smith, Harold to [Jeanette?], Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Smith, Harold: Unidentified Fragment, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Harold: Unidentified Fragment, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)